<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Matthew Andreotta</title>
<link>https://matt-lab.github.io/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://matt-lab.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Matthew Andreotta | Postdoctoral Fellow | CSIRO</description>
<image>
<url>https://matt-lab.github.io/assets/images/me.jfif</url>
<title>Matthew Andreotta</title>
<link>https://matt-lab.github.io/index.html</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.0.38</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 16:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>New project: Moralisation of Marine Resources</title>
  <dc:creator>Matthew Andreotta</dc:creator>
  <link>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-05-02_moral-tracing/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>📣 I’m excited to announce a new project 📣</p>
<p>As part of my postdoctoral research at <a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/about">CSIRO</a>, I’ll be exploring public views of marine resources.</p>
<p>👟 The first steps of this project will review how marine resources become entwined with moral judgements.</p>
<section id="why-study-public-views-of-marine-resources" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-study-public-views-of-marine-resources">Why study public views of marine resources</h2>
<p>Marine resources and space are a heated area of conservation, economic growth, livelihood, and employment. Industry, government, academia, and the public (and different subgroups amongst them) will inevitably hold different expectations, aspirations, and concerns about how society should use marine resources. If not properly managed, concerns and unfulfilled aspirations may erode public acceptance of industry activity and government policy.</p>
<p>Concerns, fears, and expectations are social constructs. They arise within groups when people share knowledge and opinions, drawing on past experiences, analogies, aspirations about the future, perceptions of costs and benefits and power relations, among other drivers. At times, these fears and expectations feature in public discourse, such as traditional media, social media, and academia, where they develop into narratives defining a problem in novel or pre-existing terms. Some of the most divisive narratives are moral. That is, discussions can become embedded with core beliefs and convictions concerning what is right and wrong. This transforms discussions of a specific marine resource to discussions of society and identity. As a result, people who hold moralised perspectives tend to be harder to persuade<sup>1</sup> and more hostile to those with opposing views<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p>Social media is particularly fertile ground for moralisation. Moralised content is more likely to receive comments, and these comments tend to be moralised<sup>3</sup>. This effect, known as a moral contagion, suggests moralised discourse is likely to proliferate through social media networks. But we know little about how moralised discourse evolves over long time periods and what events might trigger lasting changes in the way the public moralise marine issues. For this reason, I’ll be exploring how and which marine resources are moralised. If this sounds interesting to you, please get in touch.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-people-moralise-marine-resources" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-people-moralise-marine-resources">How do people moralise marine resources?</h2>
<p><a href="https://moralfoundations.org/">Moral Foundations Theory</a> suggests there are five ways in which an issue may be moralised. The basis for moral concerns are ‘foundational’, in the sense that they are recurrent themes that transcend issues and societies. The foundation of <strong>care</strong> reflects virtues of kindness and gentleness, featured in environmental concerns about harming ‘mother earth’, animal life, and fellow humans. The foundation of <strong>fairness</strong> reflects virtues of justice, rights, and reciprocity, featured in environmental concerns about justice for future generations who might carry the cost of today’s generation. The foundation of <strong>loyalty</strong> reflects virtues of patriotism and self-sacrifice for one’s in-group, featured in concerns that national economic performance may be weakened to sustain the environment. The foundation of <strong>respect</strong> reflects virtues of leadership and followership, featured in concerns about traditions surrounding natural resources. The foundation of <strong>sanctity</strong> reflects an eclectic range of virtues of cleanliness, holiness, and self-control, featured in environmental concerns for pollution and religious concerns for the environment.</p>
<div class="column-body">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-05-02_moral-tracing/https:/upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b9/An_illustration_of_Moral_foundations_Theory_created_by_Aprilia_Muktirina.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">An illustration of Moral Foundations Theory created by <a href="https://www.behance.net/heyapriliaa/projects">Aprilia Muktirina</a> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">CC BY 4.0</a></figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>As part of this research, I’ll be examining moral content at different granular levels using a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_language_processing">natural language processing</a> algorithm. At the broadest level, I’ll explore whether discussions tap into any moral concern. At the most granular level, I’ll explore what specific moral foundations are involved in discussions.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-data-will-be-used" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-data-will-be-used">What data will be used?</h2>
<p>I’ll be using data from Twitter. If you have ever posted a tweet about a marine resource, your data might be used in this study. For now, I will be using an <a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/research/technology-space/ai/emergency-situation-awareness">archive of Australian tweets curated by CSIRO</a>. In the future, I might use Twitter’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/API">application programming interface (API)</a> to access tweets from across the globe.</p>
<p>Twitter once offered researchers liberal access to data for free. Now, Twitter’s API is prohibitively expensive, costing upwards of $42,000 per month for most research purposes. This change has reduced Twitter’s transparency and accountability, obstructing research on democracy, public health, and public goods<sup>4</sup>. I hope Twitter will reconsider their position. If you have the same hope, please consider signing <a href="https://independenttechresearch.org/letter-twitter-api-access-threatens-public-interest-research/">this letter by the Coalition for Independent Technology Research</a> to call on Twitter and policymakers for reliable access to data.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-privacy-will-be-protected" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-privacy-will-be-protected">How privacy will be protected</h2>
<p>On many social media platforms, such as Twitter, Australians are protected by the Privacy Act 1988 (Cth) (Privacy Act)<sup>5</sup>. This project will handle information in accordance with the Privacy Act and the National Health &amp; Medical Research Council (NH&amp;MRC) National Statement on Ethical Conduct in Human Research (2007, updated 2018), or as otherwise required by law.</p>
<p>For this project and related scientific research, personal information included in Twitter data, such as the content of tweets and user names, will be collected. Although most Twitter data will not contain sensitive information, some information collected may be sensitive, such as text indicating ethnicity, images of people, or audio of voices. Disclosing this information to other parties is within Twitter’s purview, as per their terms and conditions for users. Consequently, this information will be collected without participant consent to this specific project.</p>
<p>Tweets from public figures and organisations may be shared verbatim, such as quoted in publications (e.g., peer-reviewed publications in academic journals). For other users, results from the project will be de-identified and/or aggregated. While CSIRO will make all attempts to ensure that these users cannot be reidentified from the information contained within the publications, this risk can never be completely removed. It is possible that a user may be able to be reidentified within the publications due to the tweets being available in a public forum.</p>
<p>For information about how Twitter generally handle personal information, please refer to <a href="https://developer.twitter.com/en/developer-terms/agreement-and-policy">the requirements for accessing Twitter data</a>. If you use Twitter and would like to avoid your Twitter data being used for research, consider deleting tweets or activating a protected status.</p>
<p>For further information on how CSIRO handles personal information and CSIRO’s access, correction, and complaints process please read the privacy policy available on <a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/about/policies/privacy">CSIRO’s website</a> or by contacting the privacy team at <a href="mailto:privacy@csiro.au">privacy@csiro.au</a>.</p>
<p>This proposed research has been approved by CSIRO’s Human Research Ethics Committee (reference number: 180/22).</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Rabia I. Kodapanakkal and colleagues have <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/09567976211040803">conducted experiments on the impact of moral and non-moral language on attitudes</a>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Kristin N. Garrett and Alexa Bankert explored how <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S000712341700059X">moral conviction heightens tensions between American partisans</a>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>This is explored in work by <a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1618923114">William Brady and colleagues</a> and <a href="https://psyarxiv.com/t9dre/">Curtis Puryear’s team</a>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>The changes and impacts are described in more detail in an <a href="https://independenttechresearch.org/letter-twitters-new-api-plans-will-devastate-public-interest-research/">April letter by the Coalition for Independent Technology Research</a>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>For more information on Australian’s privacy rights on social media, please read <a href="https://www.oaic.gov.au/privacy/your-privacy-rights/social-media-and-online-privacy/social-media">this webpage</a> by the Australian Government’s Office of the Australian Information Commissioner.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{andreotta2023,
  author = {Matthew Andreotta},
  title = {New Project: {Moralisation} of {Marine} {Resources}},
  date = {2023-05-02},
  url = {https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-05-02_moral-tracing},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-andreotta2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthew Andreotta. 2023. <span>“New Project: Moralisation of Marine
Resources.”</span> May 2, 2023. <a href="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-05-02_moral-tracing">https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-05-02_moral-tracing</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>project</category>
  <category>marine</category>
  <category>public perceptions</category>
  <category>moral</category>
  <guid>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-05-02_moral-tracing/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b9/An_illustration_of_Moral_foundations_Theory_created_by_Aprilia_Muktirina.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>First impressions of Observable JS: A language for interactive data visualisations</title>
  <dc:creator>Matthew Andreotta</dc:creator>
  <link>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/observablehq/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Visualising text data is difficult and interactive visualisations might help.</p>
<p>When analysing text, often I want to visualise the aggregate characteristic of a document or corpus. For example, in a sentiment analysis, I might want to showing the average number of words associated with each emotion in each document. This reduces entire documents to a single point on a visualisation, which can allow readers to intuitively grasp the variation of emotions between documents. But, this form of visualisation does not give readers an intuitive sense of which part of a document contains emotional content, or even what word is related to which emotion. The most curious of readers might read up on the details of the sentiment analysis, but many won’t, leaving readers untrusting or uncertain of the analysis and results.</p>
<p>I think interactive data visualisations can help here. Broadly, interactive data visualisations are graphical representations of data which respond to user input, such as a click of a mouse or numbers typed into a keyboard. Interaction can be used to clarify specific data values or hand over control to readers. For example, the graphic below represents the number of Australians for each year of age, as per the most recent national census. Deeper reds indicate more Aussies are of a certain age. We can see quickly that there is higher number of Australians aged 48 to 50, compared the Australians in their mid-40s and early-50s. More interested users can hover their house over a cell to see the exact number of Australians of any age, known as a tooltip. With minimal space, we can represented both proportional numbers (via colours) and absolute numbers (via tooltips).</p>
<div class="cell" data-warning.hidden="true" data-message.hidden="true">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code hidden" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Load libraries</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">library</span>(readr)</span>
<span id="cb1-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">library</span>(tidyr)</span>
<span id="cb1-4"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">library</span>(dplyr)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stderr hidden">
<pre><code>
Attaching package: 'dplyr'</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stderr hidden">
<pre><code>The following objects are masked from 'package:stats':

    filter, lag</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stderr hidden">
<pre><code>The following objects are masked from 'package:base':

    intersect, setdiff, setequal, union</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code hidden" id="cb5" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb5-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;"># Load 2021 Australian census data on age and gender</span></span>
<span id="cb5-2">census_data <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">read_csv</span>(</span>
<span id="cb5-3">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">file =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"https://raw.githubusercontent.com/matt-lab/2021_census_stats/main/data/2021_sex-and-age.csv"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb5-4">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">col_names =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">c</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">'age'</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">'male'</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">'female'</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">'total'</span>),</span>
<span id="cb5-5">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">col_select =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">c</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">'age'</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">'total'</span>),</span>
<span id="cb5-6">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">col_types =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">list</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">col_integer</span>()),</span>
<span id="cb5-7">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">skip =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span>,</span>
<span id="cb5-8">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;">show_col_types =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;">FALSE</span>)</span>
<span id="cb5-9"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">ojs_define</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;">census_data =</span> census_data)</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code hidden" id="cb6" data-startfrom="56" data-source-offset="-48" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode js code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode javascript" style="counter-reset: source-line 55;"><span id="cb6-56">census_data_transposed <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">transpose</span>(census_data)</span>
<span id="cb6-57"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;">import</span> {addTooltips} <span class="im" style="color: #00769E;">from</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"@mkfreeman/plot-tooltip"</span></span>
<span id="cb6-58"></span>
<span id="cb6-59"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">addTooltips</span>(</span>
<span id="cb6-60">  Plot<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">barX</span>(census_data_transposed<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">,</span> {</span>
<span id="cb6-61">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">x</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"age"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb6-62">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">interval</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">1</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb6-63">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">fill</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"total"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb6-64">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">inset</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">0</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">,</span> </span>
<span id="cb6-65">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">title</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> (d) <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;">=&gt;</span> d<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;">total</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">" Australians"</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;">\n</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;"> are "</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> d<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">.</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;">age</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">+</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">" years old"</span></span>
<span id="cb6-66">  })<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">.</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;">plot</span>({</span>
<span id="cb6-67">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">color</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> {</span>
<span id="cb6-68">      <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">type</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"linear"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb6-69">      <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">scheme</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"reds"</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">,</span> </span>
<span id="cb6-70">      <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">legend</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;">false</span></span>
<span id="cb6-71">    }<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb6-72">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">x</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> {<span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">label</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;">"Age (years)"</span>}<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">,</span></span>
<span id="cb6-73">    <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">style</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> {<span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;">paddingTop</span><span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;">:</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;">50</span>}</span>
<span id="cb6-74">  })</span>
<span id="cb6-75">)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-1" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-2" data-nodetype="declaration">

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display">
<div>
<div id="ojs-cell-1-3" data-nodetype="expression">

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The graphic above was made using the language of <a href="https://quarto.org/docs/interactive/ojs/">Observable JS</a>. The creators of the language run a website called <a href="https://observablehq.com/">ObservableHQ</a>, where users can create notebooks of all kinds of interesting visualisations. I took my first steps into Observable JS with <a href="https://observablehq.com/@observablehq/datavizcourse">a data visualisation course</a> run by <a href="https://observablehq.com/@rkosara">Robert Kosara</a>. I thought it was a useful primer for general data visualisation, Observable JS, and ObservableHQ.</p>
<p>As part of the course, I explored <a href="https://observablehq.com/@observablehq/pizza-paradise-data">pizza orders</a>. I found Veggie pizza was the seasonal underdog. In 2022, Californians purchases of <span style="color:#40B0A6"><strong>Veggie pizza</strong></span> was the most volatile <span style="color:#D3D3D3"><strong>of all pizzas</strong></span> across the year, with peaks on <span style="color:#E1BE6A"><strong>public holidays</strong></span>.</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="476" frameborder="0" src="https://observablehq.com/embed/21f984807f478fbd?cells=veggieSpending">
</iframe>
<p>ObservableHQ notebooks are really neat. But, if you prefer <code>R</code>, check out how to make <a href="https://quarto.org/docs/interactive/ojs/">interactive documents by combining Observable JS and R</a>.</p>
<p>I’ll definitely be using Observable JS in the future!</p>


<!-- -->


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{andreotta2023,
  author = {Matthew Andreotta},
  title = {First Impressions of {Observable} {JS:} {A} Language for
    Interactive Data Visualisations},
  date = {2023-04-21},
  url = {https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/observablehq},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-andreotta2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthew Andreotta. 2023. <span>“First Impressions of Observable JS: A
Language for Interactive Data Visualisations.”</span> April 21, 2023. <a href="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/observablehq">https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/observablehq</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>data visualisation</category>
  <category>observable</category>
  <category>training</category>
  <guid>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/observablehq/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/observablehq/thumbnail.svg" medium="image" type="image/svg+xml"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New article: “Does pain matter in the Australian Royal Commission into Aged Care Quality and Safety? A text mining study”</title>
  <dc:creator>Matthew Andreotta</dc:creator>
  <link>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-27_new-article/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In the early months of 2022, I worked as a researcher for <em>HammondCare</em>, a not-for-profit Australian organisation. HammondCare delivers aged care and health services in hospital, residential, home, and community settings. During my time with the organisation, I worked with a team of scientists to research and improve aged care practices. This goal was critical, as in 2021, an Australian Royal Commission into Aged Care Quality and Safety recommended a profound shift in practices, in order to “provide high quality care that is predictable, reliable and delivered through a system which is sustainable” (<a href="https://agedcare.royalcommission.gov.au/publications/final-report-volume-1">The Royal Commission’s Final Report</a> pg., 3). From my time with HammondCare, I helped write <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/08854726.2022.2091837">a peer-reviewed feasibility study of a digital tool to track pastoral care activities</a>, a <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/ajag.13121">letter to the editor on the adoption of a mobile service funded by the Australian Government to respond to severe or very severe behaviours of people with dementia living in residential aged care homes</a>, and <a href="https://alz-journals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/alz.065304">a short piece on the co-prescription of multiple classes of psychotropics to people with neuropsychiatric symptoms referred to an Australian dementia support service</a>. But in a new article published at <em>Aging and Health Research</em>, my HammondCare colleagues and I studied the Royal Commission itself.</p>
<p>The Royal Commission into Aged Care Quality and Safety received a total of 10,574 submissions, 6,800 telephone calls to an information line, and heard 641 witnesses. These submissions lead to two reports: an Interim Report in 2019 and a Final Report in 2021. In the Interim and Final Report, we found mentions of the word “pain”. This is isn’t entirely surprising, given pain affects the vast majority of older Australians, and is often under-diagnosed and under-treated. What was surprising was that in the Royal Commissions 148 recommendations to improve aged care, there was not a single mention of the word pain. Although the Royal Commission discussed pain in their reports, the topic was omitted from recommendations, reflecting a lack of attention to the presented evidence. Without specific recommendations for pain management, a disconnection may arise between targeted polices, funding schemes, and the clinical practice. Thus, older adults living in the community and residential aged care homes may remain vulnerable. If this topic interests you, you can read more about it in the open access article at <em>Aging and Health Research</em> <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2667032123000100">here</a>.</p>
<div class="column-body-outset">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-27_new-article/thumbnail.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Word cloud of the 400 most frequently occurring terms across the Royal Commission reports</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{andreotta2023,
  author = {Matthew Andreotta},
  title = {New Article: “{Does} Pain Matter in the {Australian} {Royal}
    {Commission} into {Aged} {Care} {Quality} and {Safety?} {A} Text
    Mining Study”},
  date = {2023-02-27},
  url = {https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-27_new-article},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-andreotta2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthew Andreotta. 2023. <span>“New Article: <span>‘Does Pain Matter in
the Australian Royal Commission into Aged Care Quality and Safety? A
Text Mining Study’</span>.”</span> February 27, 2023. <a href="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-27_new-article">https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-27_new-article</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>article</category>
  <category>aged care</category>
  <guid>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-27_new-article/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-27_new-article/thumbnail.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Helpful Australian demographics for building representative samples of adults</title>
  <dc:creator>Matthew Andreotta</dc:creator>
  <link>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-03_census/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>When trying to match Australia’s population demographics to my survey sample’s demographics, I sometimes find the Australian Bureau of Statistics’ reporting cumbersome. Namely, ten-year and five-year categorisation of ages combines children and adults in a 15-19 year category. This leaves me scratching my head over how many 18 and 19 year olds to include in my study of Australian adults. To alleviate this problem, I’ve reported some census statistics on Australian adults, which you can find <a href="https://matt-lab.github.io/2021_census_stats/">here</a>.</p>
<p>Maybe they will help you too?</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{andreotta2023,
  author = {Matthew Andreotta},
  title = {Helpful {Australian} Demographics for Building Representative
    Samples of Adults},
  date = {2023-02-03},
  url = {https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-03_census},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-andreotta2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthew Andreotta. 2023. <span>“Helpful Australian Demographics for
Building Representative Samples of Adults.”</span> February 3, 2023. <a href="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-03_census">https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-03_census</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>survey</category>
  <category>data collection</category>
  <category>method</category>
  <guid>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-03_census/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2023-02-03_census/thumbnail.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New article: “Evidence for three distinct climate change audience segments with varying belief updating tendencies”</title>
  <dc:creator>Matthew Andreotta</dc:creator>
  <link>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-06_new-article/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>My research paper, titled “Evidence for three distinct climate change audience segments with varying belief updating tendencies: Implications for climate change communication” has just been accepted for publication in <em>Climatic Change</em>. Co-authored by my PhD supervisors, the paper describes the survey and psychological experiments from the final chapters of my PhD thesis. We identified three segments of Australians with different perceptions of climate change, where each segment was underscored by a unique signature of psychological characteristics and belief-updating tendencies. Based on these psychological profiles, we recommend specific strategies for communicating climate change with each segment.</p>
<p>The abstract for the peer-reviewed research paper is available below:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Mounting evidence suggests members of the general public are not homogeneous in their receptivity to climate science information. Studies segmenting climate change views typically deploy a top-down approach, whereby concepts salient in scientific literature determine the number and nature of segments. In contrast, in two studies using Australian citizens, we used a bottom-up approach, in which segments were determined from perceptions of climate change concepts derived from citizen social media discourse. In Study 1, we identified three segments of the Australian public (Acceptors, Fencesitters, and Sceptics) and their psychological characteristics. We find segments differ in climate change concern and scepticism, mental models of climate, political ideology, and worldviews. In Study 2, we examined whether reception to scientific information differed across segments using a belief-updating task. Participants reported their beliefs concerning the causes of climate change, the likelihood climate change will have specific impacts, and the effectiveness of Australia’s mitigation policy. Next, participants were provided with the actual scientific estimates for each event and asked to provide new estimates. We find significant heterogeneity in the belief-updating tendencies of the three segments that can be understood with reference to their different psychological characteristics. Our results suggest tailored scientific communications informed by the psychological profiles of different segments may be more effective than a `one-size-fits-all’ approach. Using our novel audience segmentation analysis, we provide some practical suggestions regarding how communication strategies can be improved by accounting for segments’ characteristics.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You can read more about this research in the <a href="https://psyarxiv.com/64j7g" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">freely-available preprint</a>.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{andreotta2022,
  author = {Matthew Andreotta},
  title = {New Article: “{Evidence} for Three Distinct Climate Change
    Audience Segments with Varying Belief Updating Tendencies”},
  date = {2022-10-06},
  url = {https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-06_new-article},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-andreotta2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthew Andreotta. 2022. <span>“New Article: <span>‘Evidence for Three
Distinct Climate Change Audience Segments with Varying Belief Updating
Tendencies’</span>.”</span> October 6, 2022. <a href="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-06_new-article">https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-06_new-article</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>article</category>
  <category>climate change</category>
  <category>public perceptions</category>
  <guid>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-06_new-article/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-06_new-article/thumbnail.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="96" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New website, thanks to Quarto</title>
  <dc:creator>Matthew Andreotta</dc:creator>
  <link>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-04_new-website/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Today, I upload a new version of my academic website. All thanks to the magic of <span class="emoji" data-emoji="sparkles">✨</span> Quarto <span class="emoji" data-emoji="sparkles">✨</span>.</p>
<p>For the unaware, Quarto is an open-source publishing system. I first started using Quarto to seamlessly use Python and R in the same markdown document. But Quarto can do so much more: books, presentations, and of course, websites.</p>
<p>Overall, the process of building rather painless. Partly because Quarto has comprehensive documentation and partly because I followed the footsteps of those before me. For readers interested in building a website with Quarto, here are the websites I found useful:</p>
<section id="foundations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="foundations">Foundations</h2>
<ul>
<li>Creating a website |  <a href="https://quarto.org/docs/websites/">Quarto documentation</a></li>
<li>Creating your personal website using Quarto, by Sam Csik |  <a href="https://ucsb-meds.github.io/creating-quarto-websites/">Blog post</a></li>
<li>We don’t talk about Quarto, by Alison Hill |  <a href="https://www.apreshill.com/blog/2022-04-we-dont-talk-about-quarto/">Blog post</a></li>
<li>Quarto for the curious, by Tom Mock |  <a href="https://thomasmock.quarto.pub/quarto-curious/#/TitleSlide">Slides</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="tips-and-tricks" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tips-and-tricks">Tips and tricks</h2>
<ul>
<li>Quarto for an Academic Website by Drew Dimmery |  <a href="https://ddimmery.com/posts/quarto-website/">Blog post</a></li>
<li>Porting a distill blog to quarto, by Danielle Navarro |  <a href="https://blog.djnavarro.net/posts/2022-04-20_porting-to-quarto/">Blog post</a></li>
<li>A Quarto tip a day keeps the docs away, by Mine Çetinkaya-Rundel |  <a href="https://mine-cetinkaya-rundel.github.io/quarto-tip-a-day/about.html">Blog post</a> |  <a href="https://twitter.com/quarto_pub/status/1552632464907988992">Twitter</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="visuals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visuals">Visuals</h2>
<ul>
<li>Some emojis supported by Quarto |  <a href="https://gist.github.com/rxaviers/7360908">Github gist</a></li>
<li>Bootstrap icons supported by Quarto |  <a href="https://icons.getbootstrap.com/">Icons</a></li>
<li>Font awesome extension for Quarto |  <a href="https://github.com/quarto-ext/fontawesome">Extension</a> |  <a href="https://fontawesome.com/search?m=free">Icons</a></li>
<li>Unsplash, a database of photos for free use |  <a href="https://unsplash.com/">Photos</a> |  <a href="https://unsplash.com/license">License</a></li>
<li>Pexels, another database of photos for free use |  <a href="https://www.pexels.com/">Photos</a> |  <a href="https://www.pexels.com/license/">License</a></li>
<li>Bootswatch, free out-of-the-box colour schemes for your Quarto documents |  <a href="https://bootswatch.com/">Palettes</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{andreotta2022,
  author = {Matthew Andreotta},
  title = {New Website, Thanks to {Quarto}},
  date = {2022-10-04},
  url = {https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-04_new-website},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-andreotta2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Matthew Andreotta. 2022. <span>“New Website, Thanks to Quarto.”</span>
October 4, 2022. <a href="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-04_new-website">https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-04_new-website</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>website</category>
  <category>quarto</category>
  <guid>https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-04_new-website/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://matt-lab.github.io/posts/2022-10-04_new-website/thumbnail.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="96" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
